[MUSIC]
信賴區間
In this lecture, we'll talk about how you can quantify the uncertainty surrounding
這一講談的是如何運用信賴區間量化不確定的估計值
estimates with confidence intervals.
We'll talk about the relationship between confidence intervals and P values,
以下將談到信賴區間與p值的關係
and how to correctly interpret a confidence interval.
還有如何正確解讀信賴區間
Now, if we do research, we very often collect data from a specific sample
很多研究是依目的收集特定樣本的資料
with the goal to generalize to an entire population.
再根據分析推測母群
It's very often not feasible to collect information from the entire population.
但通常無法收集整個母群的資訊
If you examine people,
就像每一份問卷調查
then you cannot ask your questionnaire to everybody who's alive in the world.
不可能收集到全世界人類的回覆
Now, sometimes it might be possible to get measurements from the entire population.
只有少數狀況才會收集到完整的母群資料
Let's say that your population is all human beings who ever walked on the moon.
就像對象是至今為止曾登陸月球的太空人們
Well, there are only 12 people who've done this so far, the 12 people on this slide.
只有這張投影片列出的十二位
So if you want to know something about these 12 people, for example,
如果你的研究對象是曾經登月的太空人
their length, then you can just calculate it.
全部都在在這裡了
You don't need any statistics.
不需要任何統計
You don't need to generalize to a population because you've measured
也不必做任何推測
因為這十二位就是整個母群
the entire population.
也不必做任何推測
因為這十二位就是整個母群
Now most research, this is not feasible, so you collect data from a sample and
大多數研究很難收集完整的母群
只能從收集一部分樣本資料
then you try to generalize from this sample to the population.
然後以樣本推測母群
And whenever you do this, there's always some uncertainty.
然而推測總會有不確定的部分
Now, it's very important to always quantify and report the uncertainty
報告必須呈現估計不確定性的數量訊息
就像效果量的測量一樣
surrounding point estimates, for example an effect size measure.
報告必須呈現估計不確定性的數量訊息
就像效果量的測量一樣
Whenever you report a statistic that's very important, such as an effect size,
要呈現效果量統計結果的報告
you have to report a confidence interval around this effect size estimate.
必須包括估計的信賴區間
We can visualize this.
以這個視覺化範例說明
In this case, we have a correlation.
這個散佈圖已計算出相關係數
And we've plotted the correlation between two variables.
表示兩個變項之間的相關性
In this graph, we've visualize the uncertainty around the correlation between
這圖呈現雙胞胎之間的智商相關程度與不確定性
made up data of an IQ of one twin, and the IQ of the other twin.
We can see that this IQ score is related.
相關係數表示智商有相關性
There's a positive correlation of 0.52, but
兩者間有0.52的正相關
of course our correlation is an estimate from a sample.
只是這結果是從部分樣本估計得出
If we want to generalize this to the population,
如果要類推到母群
then there's always some uncertainty and
必須要考慮估計的不確定性
in this case, the uncertainty is illustrated by the blue area.
也就是圖中藍色區域
The blue area illustrates a 95% confidence interval.
藍色區域表示95%信賴區間
But how should you interpret a 95% confidence interval?
但是要如何去解讀呢？
Confidence intervals are a statement about the percentage of future confidence
信賴區間是一段數值區間
宣告真實參數值存在於區間之內的百分比
intervals that contain the true parameter value.
信賴區間是一段數值區間
宣告真實參數值存在於區間之內的百分比
Now, this is not very intuitive.
這種宣告並非臆測
You might think that a single confidence interval contains
設想一段信賴區間有95%的機會包含母群參數
the true population parameter, 95% of the time.
That would make sense and if a non-statistician might come up with
非統計專業人士以信賴區間呈現報告
a confidence interval, the concept of a confidence interval.
都是想要運用這樣的概念
That's probably what we wanted to be.
表達當下研究結果的確定性
But that's not how they work.
然而實際確非如此
The confidence interval is a frequentist concept.
信賴區間是次數主義的概念
It means that they apply to the long run.
表達一項研究執行重覆執行之後
Now in the long run, 95%
這些結果之中有95%包含真實參數值
of future confidence intervals will contain the true parameter value.
So the true effect size, for example, in the population.
就像是母群的真實效果量
Because this is counter-intuitive, let's try to visualize it.
因為很難想像，讓我們看這個視覺化範例
In this illustration, which we again take from rpsychologist.com, you can see many,
這張圖也是取自rpsychologist.com
many different confidence intervals for the same simulated study.
模擬一項研究重覆數次的信賴區間
We see blue dots, which are the sample estimates,
其中的藍點都是樣本估計值
the effect sizes from the sample that we collected.
表示樣本估計的效果果量
And the black line is the 95% confidence interval.
每點黑線都是95%信賴區間
Now most of the black lines contain the true sample mean.
大部分的黑線都包含真實的平均值
In this case, the true sample mean is zero.
這個例子的真實平均值是0
And we see that most of the black lines touch upon zero.
大部分黑線都與標記0的垂直線相交
Sometimes they don't.
只有少數沒有
We calculate it at 95% confidence interval.
之所以稱為95%信賴區間
So 5% of the time in the long run, we
是因為其中5%的模擬結果信賴區間並未
包合真實參數值
will get a confidence interval that does not contain the true population parameter.
是因為其中5%的模擬結果信賴區間並未
包合真實參數值
These are illustrated by the black arrows and they are visualized by red lines.
圖中黑色箭頭與紅線就是未包含的模擬結果
So the red lines do not contain the true population parameter.
我們可以計算紅線的數量比例
And this will happen in the long run, approximately 5% of the time.
得知重覆執行之後，有5%的結果不包含真實參數值
Now it's also clear that randomly chosen single confidence interval here does
這也說明為何隨機獲得一種結果
not contain the true population parameter 95% of the time.
並不是指這道信賴區間有95%的機會包含真實參數值
And in the assignment, we'll focus a little bit more on this.
本週作業裡，你將更深入探討其中原理
So 95% of future,
了解為何95%
95% confidence intervals will contain the true population parameter in the long run.
是指所有再現結果中的95%包含真實參數值
Never forget that this is a frequentist concept.
請記住這是次數主義的概念
A single confidence interval after you've collected the data,
一次研究結果的信賴區間
either contains the true population parameter or it does not.
可能會，也可能不會包含真實參數值
So in this case, you either have it or you don't, but you never know which it is.
只看一次結果，永遠不可能知道有沒有包含
But in the long run, you can say that 95% of
只有重覆再現數次
confidence intervals will contain the true population parameter.
才能歸納其中95%包括的數值是真實參數值
You can calculate the confidence interval around almost any estimate.
任何統計估計值都可以計算信賴區間
But most commonly, we calculate confidence intervals around means or
只是比較常見的是平均值、平均值差異
mean differences or effect sizes.
還有效果量的信賴區間
And it's very recommended to report them around effect sizes if you report effect
如果研究報告經常呈現效果量
sizes, which you should always do.
最好一併呈現信賴區間
So how do you calculate a 95% confidence interval or
那要如何計算95%的信賴區間呢？
different size confidence interval?
Again, there's nothing magical about 95%.
方法一樣非常簡單
You can calculate a 90% confidence interval or a 99% confidence interval,
可以的話
你也能計算90%或99%的信賴區間
if you want to.
可以的話
你也能計算90%或99%的信賴區間
For the 95% confidence interval around the mean,
以平均值的95%信賴區間來說
you calculate it by taking the mean and then adding or
只要把平均值加上還有減去
subtracting the critical Zed value multiplied by the standard error.
臨界的Z值與標準誤的乘積
Now, it's okay if you don't immediately remember what the standard error is.
沒辦法立刻想起標準誤怎麼算也OK
The standard error is the standard deviation divided by the square root of N,
標準誤就是標準差除以N的開根號
and N is the sample size.
N就是樣本數
So you can see that the larger the sample that we get,
因此樣本數越大
the smaller the standard error.
標準誤就越小
And as a consequence, the smaller the confidence interval.
得到的信賴區間也會越小
If you want to calculate a 95% confidence interval around a mean then,
如果要計算的是平均值的95%信賴區間
based on the normal distribution, you would multiply the standard error by 1.96.
是根據常態分配，只要將標準誤乘以1.96
This is a value that you see quite often in calculating confidence intervals.
1.96在信賴區間的計算非常常見
It's good to know that this is just the critical Zed value for a two-sided test.
因為1.96是雙側檢定的臨界Z值
So you're very often see this 1.96 value when people calculate confidence
所以常用的人對這數值相當熟悉
intervals.
So as the sample size increases, confidence intervals become more narrow.
那麼樣本數增加，信賴區間越小是怎麼回事
Let's visualize this.
我們來看這個視覺化範例
In this graph, we can see an increasing sample size in the horizontal axis.
這張圖的橫軸是樣本數，最多是500
It goes to 100, 200, 300, 400 participants in a two-sided D test.
設定進行每個指定人數的t檢定模擬
On the vertical axis, we've plotted the effects size, and
垂直軸是效果量
in this simulation there's no true effect.
模擬沒有真實效果的實驗
In other words, the effects size is zero and
所以效果量為0時
we see that the effect size estimate varies around this value of zero.
實驗結果的估計值在0的上下擺盪
The dotted lines are the 95% confidence interval.
虛線正是95%信賴區間的邊界
And we see that as the sample size increases,
隨著樣本數增加
the 95% confidence interval becomes more narrow.
95%信賴區間逐漸縮短
In this simulation,
在這個模擬範例
the effect size actually stays very nicely between the 95% confidence interval.
模擬出來的效果量都在95%信賴區間之內
But sometimes, 5% of the time, the simulation will give you
然而大約有5%的模擬結果會超過這個範圍
an effect size measure that falls just outside of these 95% confidence borders.
Now it's very important not to incorrectly interpret the confidence interval.
誤讀信賴區間的意義是很嚴重的
And regrettably, the most intuitive interpretation is incorrect.
可惜的是，許多書藉文章的解讀是錯誤的
You might feel that if you have a single 95% confidence interval.
有人認為根據一次結果95%的信賴區間
Then 95% of future estimates will fall within this single confidence interval.
未來相同的實驗，
有95%的結果就會是區間之內
But a confidence interval is a statement about future confidence intervals.
然而信賴區間只是宣告未來可能得到的信賴區間
It's not a statement about future estimates.
而非宣告可能得到的估計值
It says that 95% of future confidence intervals will contain the true
它只表示將產出的信賴區間有95%包含母群參數值
population parameter.
You can take a look at how often a single 95% confidence
也可以從另一個角度看單一的95%信賴區間
interval will contain the true population parameter.
會包含真實母群參數的機會
Simulation studies have shown that if you perform many, many, many simulations.
以此設定做了非常非常多次的模擬結果
Then, it turns out that about 84.3% of single 95% confidence
會發現84.3%的模擬結果
intervals contain the population parameter in the long run.
顯示單一95%信賴區間包含母群參數
And this is known as a capture percentage.
84.3%被稱為佔有百分比(capture percentage)
So a single 95% confidence interval will capture the true value, 84.3% of the time.
也就是用單一信賴區間預測未來的再現結果
有84.3%的正確率
Regrettably, this varies quite a lot, it depends,
很可惜，這個數值是變動的
you never really know whether this is the case or not.
另一個研究的佔有百分比可能不是84.3%
So this is not a very usable statistic in itself, but a least it's one way to
所以信賴區間並非可靠的統計值
interpret the single 95% confidence before it gives you some idea about how often
但至少可以推測有多少實驗結果會包含真實母群參數
this single confidence interval will contain the true population parameter.
About five in six times, it will be the case.
也許六個裡頭有五個會包含
You never really know for a single observation.
但是只憑一個結果沒人能推測
Now confidence intervals and p-values are directly related.
信賴區間與p值密不可分
If a single 95% confidence interval does not contain zero,
一個95%信賴區間不包含0
it automatically implies that the p-value is smaller than 0.05.
相當於p值小於0.05
Let's take a look at a meta analysis where we've plotted effect sizes and
讓我們看一下這則整合分析的視覺範例
confidence intervals, so we can visualize this.
In this graph, we see what's know as a four split.
圖中最上面有四條黑條
Every line illustrates a single study.
分別代表單一研究結果
On the horizontal axis, we see the effects size Hedges' G.
水平線的效果量表示Hedges' g
The four studies vary in the effect size, illustrated by the yellow square.
四個研究的效果量以黃色方塊表示
Around an effect size of 0.43.
整合效果量大約是0.43
Each effect size has a 95% confidence interval,
每個研究結果效果量有95%信賴區間
visualized by the black horizontal line.
正是每條黑色水平線的範圍
If we take a look at the third study from the top, we can see that a 95%
仔細看會發現從最上頭算起第三個研究
confidence interval overlaps with the black vertical line at Hedges' G of zero.
信賴區間包含Hedges' g為0
This implies that the third study did not yield the statistically significant
這表示第三個研究結果是不顯著的
effect.
Because the 95% confidence interval around the effect size estimates contains zero.
因為這項效果量的信賴區間包含0
Now, we've been talking about confidence intervals from a frequentist perspective.
至此已說完信賴區間的次數主義觀點
And here we have the slightly counter-intuitive interpretation
解釋為何多次研究的信賴區間
of confidence intervals in the long run.
與一般人的直覺是相反的
So 95% confidence intervals will contain the true population parameter,
次數主義的解讀是所有研究結果信賴區間
會有95%包含真實母群參數
95% of the time in the long run, which is a frequentist interpretation.
次數主義的解讀是所有研究結果信賴區間
會有95%包含真實母群參數
A more intuitive interpretation is found in Bayesian statistics where people
符合一般人直覺的是貝氏統計的可信區間
calculate credible intervals.
Or a slightly different version known as in highest density interval, and
也有人稱呼最大密度區間
these can be interpreted in a more strait forward manner.
可信區間的解讀方式比信賴區間更直接
A 95% credible interval contains all of the values that you find most plausible.
95%可信區間包含的值都有可能是母群參數
In this case, you are quantifying your belief.
95%是宣告者個人信心的量化
It doesn't mean that 95% of the true population parameters indeed
並不是說真實母群參數有95%的機率落在這區間
fall within this area.
It doesn't mean that in the long run,
也不是指再做幾次相同研究
you can expect 95% of credible intervals to contain the true population parameter.
可能有95%的結果可信區間包含真實母群參數
But it quantifies your belief, these are the values that you find most plausible.
這個區間表示依照研究者的方法，
最可能找到參數的範圍
Remember that earlier, we visualized the distributions of the prior,
第一週課程曾介紹先驗機率分配
in this case, the gray line.
也就是這張圖的灰色曲線
The blue dashed line, illustrating the likelihood function which together,
藍色虛線是似然性函數的分配
create the posterior distribution illustrated by the black line.
有前兩者才能知道黑色曲線代表的事後機率分配
We can calculate the 95% credible interval,
而95%可信區間就是
the values that lie between the two shaded areas in the tails.
黑色曲線下沒有著色的區域
Confidence intervals provide some idea of what will happen in the future.
信賴區間指引之後研究的可能結果
You can use confidence intervals to quantify the uncertainty in your
可用來表示估計值不確定的部分
estimates.
Whenever you report important parameter estimates,
只要報告重要的參數估計值
such as effect sizes, you should always accompany these with confidence intervals.
像是效果量，務必一起呈現信賴區間
[MUSIC]
影片結束